Guide to the Scientists and science collection, 1870-1948
Department of Special Collections
Scientists and science collection,
1870-1948
Special Collections M0133
1.5 linear ft.
Stanford University. Libraries. Dept. of Special Collections and University Archives.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
None.
Provenance
Various sources.
Scope and Content
Single items & small collections written by or about scientists and their work. Includes letters, mss. of articles & books, clips, notes, diagrams, addresses & a journal. 1870-1948.
Container List
- Agassiz, (Jean) Louis (Rodolphe) 1807-1873 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 1872, Dec 8.to [John Franklin] Miller., ALS
    Re: fur seal skeletons, zoology of Alaska, etc.
- Baum, Frank G. (Box 1, Folder 1a)
  - Scrapbook re: Electricity in USA 1923 (June) - 1925 (Apr)
- Brown - see 2/18.
- Burgess texts n.d. (Box 1, Folder 1b)
  Aeronautics, applied mechanics, notes, photos, drawings, typescript
- Carrel, Alexis 1873 - (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 1937, Nov 8.to Ray Lyman Wilbur., TLS
- Durand, William Frederick 1859 - 1958. Giacomelli, R. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 1. 1930, Apr 13.RG to WFD., TLS.
  - 2. 1930, Apr 14.The Aerodynamics of Leonardo Da Vinci by R. Giacomelli., Typescript of booklet with ms. corrections.
  - 3. 1930, May 22.RG to WFD., TLS.
  - 4. 1930, Jul 3.RG to WFD., TLS
  - 5. 1930, Jul 3.Pages of #2 rewritten, typescript with ms. corrections.
  - 6. Figures for #2. Reproduction of Leonardo's drawings.
  - 7. Errata for #2. Typescript with ms. corrections and additions.
  - 8. 1930, Aug 5.WFD to RG., TL.
  - 9. Introduction to or summary of #2.
- Eastman, George 1854 - 1932 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 1931, Mar 18.to Ray Lyman Wilbur., TLS
- Edison, Thomas Alva 1847 - 1931 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 1925, Apr 28.to Ray Lyman Wilbur., TLS
- Einstein, Albert 1879 - 1955. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - 1. n.d.Holograph poem in German; tel. Alfred E. Cohn to AE on verso; typed Eng. Translation of poem.
  - 2. 1936, Oct 15.Algemeines uber die Schule., AMsS in German with typed English translation.
    Address delivered at Tri-Centennial Celebration of NYC Bod of Education.
- Fraser, John Edward (Box 1, Folder 7)
  Science Notes: Bound volume of mounted clippings, holograph notes and diagrams by Fraser et al, letters.
  - 1. 1882, Sept 22F.N. Menzies to Fraser., ALS.
  - 2. 1894, Jun 3.[F.?] Bailey., ALS.
  - 3. [1889], Mar 6.Bailey to Fraser., ALS.
  - 4. 1889, Jan 31.Henry Drummond to?, ALS.
  - 5. 1893, Dec 27.A.G. Butler (Butler) to Fraser, ALS.
  - 6. 1892, Dec 12.Isaac Bayley Balfour to Fraser., ALS.
  - 7. 1892, Dec 14.Balfour to Fraser. Printed receipt signed and note holograph.
  - 8. The Salmon Disease & Its Cure. Fraser holograph ms. signed.
  - 9. 1889, Apr 30.J. Anderson to Fraser., ALS.
  - 10. 1870, Nov 1.Allan MacPherson. Holograph certificate of Fraser's divinity examination.
- Henry, Joseph 1797 - 1878 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - 1874, Nov 13.to Prof. [Hans?] Barkan., ALS
- Holt, L. Emmett 1855 - 1924 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - 1921, Dec 8.to [Ray Lyman] Wilbur., ALS
- Keen, William Williams 1837 - 1932 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - 1927, Jan 20.to Ray Lyman Wilbur., TLS
- Lawrence, Ernest Orlando 1901 - (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - 1939, Nov 28.to Ray Lyman Wilbur., TLS
- MacKintosh, J.S. (Box 1, Folder 11a)
  - 1913, Apr 28.to Prof. [Bateson] & 1911reprint: The Racial Evolution of the British People: Its Importance in Pathology & Therapeutics, ALS
- Michelson, Albert Abraham 1852 - 1931 (Box 1, Folder 11b)
  - 1878.The Velocity of Light, donated by Hilding T. Eckstrom.
- Nutter, E.H. (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Emanuel Swedenborg (1688 - 1772) Scientist & Theologian. Typescript of paper read before Fortnightly Club of Redlands, 1948.
- O'Malley, Charles D. (Box 2)
  Leonardo Da Vinci, author's original typescript re: anatomy & antomical illustration.
  - 1. pp. 1-201 & 3 pp. of edited galley proof. (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - 2. pp. 202-390. (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - 3. pp. 391-569. (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Whipple, George Hoyt 1878 - (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - 1934, Nov 12.To Ray Lyman Wilbur., TLS.
- See, Jefferson, Jackson 1866 - (Oversize OS)
  Astronomer, Geometer, Certificates and Societes
- See, T.J.J. (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - 1. 1887, Apr 2. To find the relation between the mean anomaly & the real anomaly. See, TJJ to Dr. Lyman Briggs, 30 Oct. 1939, ALS with notes on verso.
  - 2. 1926, Aug 22.from M.J. Ryan., TLS
- Brown, Charles Albert 1870 - 1947 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Chemist. Record of chemical and agricultural observations in foreign countries, 1938., Ten volumes bound into two notebooks. Carbon copy (Box 3, Folder 19)
- Two additional notebooks containing Vol. I and Vol. II only of Record of chemical and agricultural observations in foreign countries, 1938. (Box 3, Folder 20-21)